Hey there.
Welcome to my session here
on DevSecOps, where I'm
gonna try and go beyond
GitHub Advanced Security.
My name is Pieter Ditender.
I'm a senior content
developer at Microsoft
Redmond, originally from
Belgium, but relocated
about five years ago.
If you have any questions
about my session, don't
hesitate reaching out.
You got all my contact details
on aka.ms/pdtit Now, when we
talk about DevSecOps, in the
Microsoft DevOps solutions,
you have Azure DevOps that's
been around for a while,
and about eight years ago,
Microsoft acquired GitHub,
where out of technology
shifts, I would say, we're
positioning GitHub a little
bit more than Azure DevOps
nowadays, but it doesn't mean
that Azure DevOps is dead.
And even more interesting is
that a lot of what I'm gonna
talk about today, although it
is GitHub security oriented,
a lot of the foundation
concepts and actually
some capabilities are also
available within Azure DevOps.
So pretty easy, pretty
cool if you ask me.
Now, when you look at GitHub
Advanced Security, it's
basically a licensing bundle
that you enable in your
GitHub enterprise environment.
Now, if you watch this session
and you go like I don't have
GitHub Enterprise, I just
have my personal account.
Can I use it?" First
of all, sure you can.
And next to that, the good
news is that a lot of the
capabilities identical
to the Enterprise GitHub
Advanced Security bundle
are already available
in public GitHub repos.
Now, if you look at what
does GitHub Advanced
Security actually stands
for it's a bundle of
three main components.
The first one is
secret scanning.
It allows you to scan
for, guess what, secrets.
There's a partnership
with give or take about 70
different partner companies
where they all provide
like the hashes, the tokens
of what their security
and secrets look like.
So if you think about Azure
resource environments where
you have Key Vault, where
you have traditional storage
account SQL connection
strings, those things.
If you store any of those
keys inside a GitHub repo
and you have secret scanning
enabled, it will get flagged
as please don't store that
secret in your repo anymore.
Even better, there is push
protection, which means that
it can actually block off
the commit into the repo from
your local machine as well.
Second component is code
scanning, where GitHub
positions CodeQL, like code
query language, and allows
you to analyze source code
in the same way you would
run queries against pretty
much any kind of data.
Super powerful and allowing
you to really customize
the queries, and I got a
few demos on that later on.
Third component is Dependabot.
Dependabot is the
vulnerability scanning
where it's gonna rely on
public open information from
the cve.org vulnerability
database, and then again
bringing in that detection
mechanism into your repos.
And next to that, also
bringing in some AI
capabilities where you can
actually hand it over to
GitHub Copilot now, and
asking you to not only detect
a problem but also mitigate
rewriting the package files,
for example, in your repos.
And then from there, allowing
you to be more more secure.
That's the main thing.
Now, from here, I could
switch to a set of demos
showing you secret scanning,
code scanning, vulnerability
scanning, but I wanted to
take it a little bit further.
So what I'm gonna do here
is going a little bit beyond
GitHub Advanced Security.
Because why would I try
to squeeze in only three
features, probably the most
important ones, the ones
you get out of the bundle,
if we do get twenty-six
letters in the alphabet?
So what I'm gonna do from
here is switching back and
forth between explaining a
little bit what I think are
the core components in overall
doing DevSecOps, integrating
security in everything you
do that's DevOps related.
Using GitHub Advanced
Security as the guidelines,
using GitHub overall
as a DevOps platform,
but then also touching
on a few other things.
Now, to keep it a bit
dynamic, I'm gonna bring in
a few short demos, but not
for each and every service
because then this session
would probably take two,
three days, and I only got
forty-five minutes to do so.
But at least I'm gonna
try and explain, and every
now and then, for one of
the key capabilities, I
think I'm gonna bring in
like short little demos.
Let's see how far
we can take this.
So let's start with the
first one here, alerts.
Security alerts tell us when
GitHub finds something that
needs attention, while audit
logs help us understand
who did what and when
across your enterprise, but
also individual accounts.
And then we have autofix.
Autofix is taking it one
step further by suggesting
practical code change
instead of only reporting
about the problem.
And then AST, or application
security testing, is
the broader practice
behind all of this.
Testing your application,
testing the code, and then
testing the behavior for
security weaknesses throughout
your entire delivery
That brings us to B,
where B in my case stands
for branch protection.
These rules protect important
branches, especially the
main branch, from any risky
or accidental changes.
Now you can require request
pull request reviews,
successful status checks, and
then bringing in what we call
signed commits, and I'll talk
about that later on, before
anything even gets merged.
Now, the point is never to
slow down your developers.
It is, however, to make them
secure, provide them a safe
path from the normal path,
and then rushing through
clicking around, maybe using
compromised accounts, no
longer being able to bypass
those security settings
Moving on, we have C. C brings
us to code scanning, which I
already briefly talked about.
By the way, that little
sparkle emphasizes that
it's a GitHub advanced
security component.
But we also have compliance
collaborators and Copilot.
I'll start with code scanning.
Code scanning uses CodeQL,
already mentioned briefly,
to find security issues
by analyzing code as data.
Compliance is obviously the
evidence that our controls
are actually being followed.
Collaborator points to
permissions, deciding who can
read, write, and basically do
whatever you want in the repo.
So access should always
match the person's role, and
maybe not just the overall
DevOps engineer role, but
literally what are the least
amount of privileges that I
need to perform this task.
And then last, GitHub Copilot,
I can only hope that all of
you are familiar with it.
GitHub Copilot is an
AI assistant helping
developers, DevOps engineers
like yourself working
faster inside any possible
editor you could think of.
But then it also provides
suggestions, code rewrites,
integrating testing, and
then if you want, you
could also use it to do
some security validation
So for this demo, I'm
splitting it up in
three different tasks
that… or sections
that I wanna show you.
The baseline code scanning,
how to enable it, and then
obviously seeing the outcome.
Then showing you a bit more
details about the CodeQL
specific actions workflow.
And then last, I'm gonna
show you what CodeQL looks
like in CLI and out of
the VS Code extension.
If you wanna follow along,
I have a public repo that's
called GH500 Code Scanning
Demo, with dashes in between
each and every word, just
to have it clear, where as
always, you already know
where to find the GitHub
Advanced Security settings.
You would go into the Security
tab, and then from here,
enabling code scanning.
Or if you have the Enterprise
version of Advanced Security
in GitHub, you would go
into the Advanced Security
settings, and then from
there, enabling the code
scanning and obviously going
through all the options that
you do have available here.
Once you enable this,
after a couple of minutes,
typically, it's gonna raise
a set of alerts, obviously
depending on your source code.
So in this sample repo, if
I open up code scanning,
it's gonna show me
four different alerts.
I'm gonna grab just
one of these, and it's
providing me insights.
Now- There's quite some,
I would say, recognizable
components here based on
what I explained using
Dependabot, but the use
case obviously is different.
Why?
Because now this time
it's not just checking
for vulnerabilities out of
the packages, which in the
end is what Dependabot is
doing, but it's now also
checking actual source code.
So it's really checking
all the code inside the
repo and identifying any
potential misconfiguration
in our code base.
So in this example here,
it's highlighting this HTML
construction, depending
on library input, might
later on allow cross-site
scripting, which might in
the end break the security
of your web application.
Little bit further
down, you can see the
tool that got detected.
This case CodeQL, but
remember, we could achieve
similar things using
third-party scanning tool.
It's gonna provide more
details like what is the risk
here, and if you open up the
More view, it's gonna show you
the recommendations, providing
you some sample code how to
make this more secured code.
Similar to Dependabot,
it's interacting with the
weaknesses, the CWEs, and from
here, you could open them up,
look into the CWE web site
or web page, where now it's
providing you more details,
more descriptive what that
cross-site scripting in this
simulation actually stands for
If we take a step back
It's gonna show us The outcome
of the actual workflow.
So that's gonna be the
second part here in the demo.
Apart from, again, the
security detection, once we
enable code scanning behind
the scenes, it's creating
an actions workflow pipeline
where it's called CodeQL.
Advanced, where obviously
just like any other actions
pipeline, you could rename
it, you can make some
modifications into it.
Where if you look into
the actual YAML file,
which I grabbed from
the marketplace, would
actually be another option.
But just by enabling
it, this is what you
get out of the box.
So what we have is the trigger
to push, which in this example
means whenever we have an
update in the main branch
or a pull request coming in
out of the main branch and
a scheduled task using the
traditional Chrome notation,
it's gonna run the job.
Now, since we're scanning
code, it runs an analysis
where in this example out
of the box, it's using the
GitHub matrix YAML syntax,
which basically means it
allows us to run this against
multiple operating systems.
Where Windows is not
part of this, but I
have no idea why not.
I think it's just an
example out of the box.
But then obviously, the most
important p-part is starting
a little bit further down,
where out of the analysis
task, we need to identify
what is that CodeQL database
that we want you to use.
And next to that, what is
the development framework
language that we're using.
Now, in this case, you can
see that our sample code
has two different languages.
You could say like the
front-end, JavaScript,
TypeScript, the back-end,
maybe C# or any other
combination of any of
these supported languages.
We're gonna check out the
repo like any other pipeline,
nothing really new here.
That's technically actually
moving or executing a Git
clone task from the repo into
the GitHub runner virtual
machine running the pipeline.
And then the most important
part here is triggering
the GitHub CodeQL action,
where it's using the
matrix language, picking
up the different builds.
And then from here, if
I zoom out and make it a
little bit bigger again,
all the way down here in
the YAML file, it's also
triggering the actual action,
performing the analysis.
Where then if we look into
the actual code Runtime.
I'm gonna open up one
of my sample runs here.
We have two jobs.
In meantime, you know where
are the two jobs coming from.
We have the C# code
scanning, we have the
JavaScript code scanning.
If I look into the C# one,
and I look a bit more into
the most important task
here, performing CodeQL, you
can see there's quite some
activity happening here.
And then zooming in a
little bit, it starts
with extracting C#.
That's like bringing in
the CodeQL database, the
queries technically, for
the C# language into the
runner performing the task.
Then a little bit
further, it's performing
the actual analysis.
If we open up the more
detailed view, you can see
here that it's now loading,
mapping it with our repo code
Loading the .NET framework,
that's all pretty obvious.
And a little bit further
here, it's triggering a build
process, .NET restore, loading
the .NET framework, loading
the assemblies, and then it's
performing the build analysis.
So just a couple of details
here, where then once our
build process is done, that's
where it starts running
the actual code scanning.
So here on the side,
these are all different
security features where
the CodeQL engine is
actually scanning for.
So those are specific QL, like
query language, syntax files.
I'll show you some of that
in the next part of my demo.
But these are all the
pre-built code scanning tasks,
you could say, the database
validation using the C#
queries coming out of the box,
out of the CodeQL framework.
Once the scanning is done,
it's running the evaluation.
And then if I move all the way
down, and you can see even for
a small sample project like
this one, it's now performing
the analysis and then
providing the actual outcome
of it Analysis is done,
extraction is done, and if
you want, you can again look
into that SARIF file as well.
The JSON file with all the
details, all the outcome.
And then from here,
you have a pretty good
view on what's actually
happening with my code.
What are the code
vulnerabilities from a coding
or code base perspective?
If I bring in my repo
in my VS Code, what I
did here is installing
the CodeQL extension.
Now, again, this repo is
public, so feel free to
maybe look into it if you
wanna get some more ideas
about sample queries.
I have a few of them, and I'll
just open up a couple of them.
So opening up my CodeQL,
and the way it's structured
is up here, you have a
section for the languages.
Like in my case, I
have two languages.
You could define which
ones do you wanna scan for.
What is the
database to be used?
And I'll make it a
little bit bigger.
So there's two
different options here.
One is the default GitHub
CodeQL, the same one that
I actually had in the
GitHub Actions workflow.
But then you could also
import your own database.
I'm using CodeQL CLI for this,
so it's basically running
CodeQL create database, and
then pointing to your actual
repo, because the database
in this case means what is
the source code reference
that I need to use to scan.
The way to do that is
go into your database.
Once obviously you create
it, you would select it.
And in this sample repo,
it would be the CodeQL
file location or folder
location in this case.
Next, we have the
actual queries.
And again, I have several
different ones wherein This
example here, I'm gonna use
example.ql, and what it's
doing, it's not, I would
say, necessarily checking
for actual security issues,
but at the same point, it's
actually a valid security
scanning where it's using
the C# language, because this
is the C# part of my app.
And what I'm gonna do here
is looking for the page model
where it's having a reference
to the logging or the logger,
but it's not being used.
And this is one of the
easier scenarios, I think.
But what I'm doing is
checking if my page model is
using the logger, yes or no.
Because it requires some
permission, and it could
technically be misused.
Where now in this case,
I'm using the logger in
my code, but then I'm
checking that it is actually
being used, yes or no.
So the page model here gives
me access to the logger, but
I'm not technically using
the logger, which would be
flagged as a security risk.
And then the last step is
obviously running the query.
And again, I got a
whole bunch of examples.
If you go to that public
repo, feel free to
have a look into them.
There's a, for example,
the cross-site scanning
for vulnerabilities.
The SQL injection could
be used, but I don't have
SQL in this code example.
Then we move into the queries,
and you could basically select
a query, right-click, Run
Against Local Database, or
depending on your setup, you
might have different options.
When you run it against
a local database, meaning
again the code base from the
repo, you can see down here
it's performing the scan.
Now, to save a bit on demo
time, I'm gonna cancel
this because I already
ran it in preparation
for my demo and I ran a
few of these, so maybe
I'm gonna remove the
ones with no outcome.
And then here on the side, you
get the actual CodeQL query
results, where it's gonna
list up all the different
parts in your code example,
where I got like a contact
form that the idea is that
you would allow customers
to provide their contact
details, and that's where I'm
having that reference to the
logger, but again not using.
There's a little flag here,
"Show results in the problems
view." It means integrated
again in VS Code, it's
gonna allow you to pull up.
And then the other nice
thing is also that it's
gonna show it right in
your actual code base.
So here on my onPost action
is getting flagged, my onPost
delete is getting flagged,
and then if you move over,
it's gonna highlight the
root cause of the problem.
So in short, that's
what CodeQL is about.
So started with the baseline
code scanning, enabling
code scanning, waiting
for the alerts to come in.
Behind the scenes, triggering
the CodeQL actions where
you got some fine-tuning
options if you want, because
they're just like any other
actions pipeline syntax.
Walk you through some of the
details, the detailed steps,
and then closing with the
experience of integrating the
CodeQL extension in VS Code
to help you writing the query,
selecting the code languages,
importing or creating your
CodeQL database, and then
eventually running the query
and seeing the outcome of it.
So I think with that, I'm
gonna close out my demo
and switching back for
a last couple of minutes
back to the presentation
That brings me to Dependabot.
So Dependabot is all about
dependencies, and I also
included dynamic testing.
Dependabot watches over your
packages inside the repos.
So raising alerts, identifying
any suspicious vulnerabilities
based on that CVE open, data
open standard, open database.
But then GitHub also brings
in their own weakness
vulnerability scanning, and
it's basically combining
those two together.
Now dependency review checks
is basically a pull request.
So if you're already familiar
with source control, with
commits, with pull requests,
in the way now you're gonna
handle your dependency
vulnerability scanning
using Dependabot is not
changing anything in your
overall way of doing DevOps.
So when it detects a
vulnerable package, it can
now be stopped before you're
gonna merge it from a feature
branch into the main branch.
And then DAST or dynamic
application security
testing is really allowing
you to test your running
application from the outside.
For example, OWASP is still
one of my favorites to do so.
Later on, I'll talk about
static analysis, which means
you're gonna scan your code,
where dynamic means you're
gonna scan your actual running
environment, preferably in
test staging development,
and maybe even in production.
But that should already
be a secured environment.
Now all of these together
provide you like validation
of security packages
during the import, during
the creation, validating
the vulnerabilities, and
then also making sure
that your application is
live in a secured state
So this demo is covering,
I would say, four
different tasks that we can
perform using Dependabot.
So I'm gonna start with
the first one that I
would describe as main
Dependabot capabilities.
I'm using a sample repo.
It's a public one, so feel
free to maybe look into
it, maybe fork it into your
own GitHub environment.
The repo is
gh-500-dependabot-demo.
What I did for this one is
going into the settings once
more And if we look into our
settings down here, we have
advanced security And we
have a set of options around
dependency graph and a full
section around Dependabot.
Now, I have to be a bit
honest here, where I'm not
using any of the enterprise
GitHub advanced security
enterprise options because I'm
using my own GitHub account.
I'm not running it in an
enterprise environment.
So that means that I would say
ninety, ninety-five percent
of what I'm gonna demo here is
identical in your environment.
But if you do this from
an enterprise account
level, you're gonna see
that you have a few more
options on organizational
level or enterprise level.
But it's basically going
to settings on organization
with a whole list of
options or even defining
them on enterprise level.
The outcome, the use case,
is technically identical
to everything I'm showing
in this part of the demo.
So once we enable Dependabot,
where you can see here
it is enabled, and we
could define some rules,
but that's fine-tuning.
Didn't do any of that to
make sure that I can show
you all default capabilities.
The outcome of that is, if
I now move to my Security
tab, and I navigate to
Dependabot here, it's
gonna show me the outcome.
By the way, although I
moved to Settings, GitHub
Advanced Security, the faster
way to enable it initially
is go into your Security
tab and making sure here
that Dependabot is enabled
Once we enable Dependabot,
after just a couple of
minutes, typically, we see
different Dependabot alerts.
So in this example, it's
some sample code, so
nothing too specific.
And obviously, it's not
about the specifics of
code, it's about detecting
those vulnerabilities.
So what we get here is a first
alert, and I got dif-- four
different ones, where we can
see that it's highlighting
what is the package, like the
application code component,
what is the affected version.
So in this case, it's
a JavaScript package
that we use, and
anything below version
four-seventeen-twenty-one is
having known vulnerabilities.
There's a short
description here, what that
vulnerability actually means.
In this case, potential
risk for command injection.
And then also important is
what is the fix, which in
this example means everything
that's newer version
four-seventeen-twenty-one
or up no longer has
that vulnerability.
We can look into a
few more details.
Now, obviously, this
is a short example,
but this explanation
could be a lot longer.
But then here on the
side, it also provides
additional information.
For example, the
CVSS information.
What is the network or what
is the attack vector, in
this case, the network?
What are some of the
impacted privileges?
And we also have an EPSS
score if you need to look
into any of those numbers for
maybe your reporting I talked
about integration with CVEs.
That's what you
have over here.
But then we also have
the CWEs, which reflects
the weakness, not just
the vulnerability.
Interesting here is when I
grab this CVE number and I
move into the actual cve.org
website, and I paste in that
information, I can actually
search for more details.
So what it provides me here is
basically the same information
that we also saw integrated
in the GitHub portal out of
the Dependabot capabilities.
It's highlighting some
additional details.
And then from here, also
useful is where other
vendors, sometimes security
vendors like Snyk as a code
scanning security tool,
obviously GitHub itself,
I'll talk about it in a
second, but then also Oracle
is listed in this example.
There's a few other where
I'm gonna highlight NetApp,
not any specific reason,
but what you could have in
this case is, for example,
NetApp, in this case, a
storage vendor, if you're
not familiar with them, also
highlights this as a security
risk, which might mean that
inside their NetApp software
products, they're actually
using that JavaScript engine.
As you can see here, it's
clearly described, and
it's now also referring to
that CVE and highlighting
the risk aspect of it.
So if you build any of your
custom software, you're
gonna integrate those
packages, but now you could
also use it to actually
validate other building
blocks in your environment.
If we switch back to
our GitHub scenario, we
also have our built-in
GitHub advisory database.
So what we can do from
here is, again, using
the GitHub definition,
GitHub clarification, how
they detected a problem.
Now, you're gonna see here
there's quite some overlap
maybe with the official
cve.org database information.
But the use case here is that
you might have a vulnerability
getting detected out of
Dependabot, which might
be listed in the GitHub
advanced advisories and
maybe not even listed in the
CVE or obviously the other
way around Got a few other
options that I wanna show you.
So let's take a step back.
Back in the repo, we have our
Dependabot, but then we also
have that dependency graph.
How do you get to
the dependency graph?
You open the repo, you
navigate to your insights,
and then here on the
side, you can pull up the
dependency graph details.
Once we navigate to
dependency graph, you're
gonna see that it's listing
up not only one package
in this case, but listing
up all possible packages.
I can use the Dependabot tab
up here, and that's gonna
show me, again, specifics
about any version updates.
'Cause remember, Dependabot
is not only used to detect
the vulnerabilities like the
vulnerable packages, but also
recommending any mitigations
and typically version updates.
So what you can do here, and
again, in this example repo,
we have a JavaScript package
JSON, so technically the text
file if you want with all
the packages that we need.
We can look into
recent updates.
Now, don't worry too much
about the error messages here.
It means that there is already
a updated version available,
so there is a pull request.
I tried multiple demos all at
the same time, and every now
and then you can imagine that
some of those are conflicting.
Now, what it gives you here
is a more detailed logging.
Now, in this case, there's
not too much, but it's
gonna show me the actual
logs of my Dependabot task.
Now, before I talk about the
tasks or my workflows, let's
take one little step back into
dependency graph, where now
we can export that software
bill of material, which
technically, again, is nothing
really more than a JSON file.
It's obviously opening it
up in VS Code in my case.
But then if I do my
formatting, you can see that
it's traditional JSON, but
all the details from the
packages that we have out of
the package manager, who's
the owner of the package,
what are the versions,
and all that information
can be reused from here
Next little piece is the
Dependabot options within
the GitHub advanced security.
So again, the starting
point could have been
go to security, enable
Dependabot, and then
read out the information.
That's typically picking
up the default options.
Now, you can make
this more granular for
your specific example.
And again, remember, I don't
have the organization or
enterprise level in my demos
just to keep it a little bit
easier and also a v-- more
applicable to everyone, not
just the customers having
the enterprise e-edition.
But what we can do here is
navigate to advanced security
and then defining specific
options for Dependabot.
So again, dependency graph,
getting more view, a better
view on your dependencies.
Enable or disable I would
recommend you to enable
it and never disabling it.
And then inside Dependabot
itself, you have a
few different options.
I'm not gonna walk you through
all these options because
they're quite specific.
But, for example, the one
that I usually enable is
the security updates, which
means there is a vulnerable
package getting detected,
and we're gonna look into it
from a security perspective.
And then maybe this one is
also allowing Dependabot to
actually open pull requests
automatically, making sure
that it's taking away some of
the manual reviewing work and
code rewriting work for you.
That's where we obviously
have an interaction
with our YAML pipelines.
So once we enable Dependabot
inside the actions, it's
creating a Dependabot
update little workflow task.
Out of that task, you can see
there's quite some history
in this sample because I've
been using this for most of
my demos on the Dependabot.
We can look into each
and every of the cycles.
My Dependabot job is running,
and then inside, you have
all the details, and this is
partly, again, JSON-based.
So if you wanna export
some of this, you can
obviously definitely do that.
And then you can see that
it's looping through different
individual tasks, and then
eventually more tasks.
And over here, it's looking
into the different Git
steps, cloning, taking
actions against the repo,
uploading the package
could be one example.
And then all the way at the
end, it's gonna highlight
the different updated
tasks that it performed
If I move to pull requests,
you can see that all of these
actions are basically linked
to those pull requests.
So a big part, I would say
the benefit of Dependabot
is not only detecting
vulnerabilities, but also
automating a big part of
the process and integrating
potential updates, making
your life as a DevOps engineer
or maybe a repo admin a
lot more User friendly.
Last part that I wanna
highlight is the Dependabot
dependency review.
So remember in the
presentation piece I talked
about it, but I didn't really
drill down on all the details,
meaning the differences
between just using Dependabot
and Dependabot dependency.
So I'm gonna explain a
little bit using the demo.
So what is the
dependency review?
It's first of all, a specific
action out of the marketplace.
So what you can do is
create a new action.
You search for dependency
review, and you're gonna
configure your task.
It's a built-in GitHub actions
task, which means down here
in my code section, we're
gonna run an action checkout,
which we always have in
GitHub actions pipelines.
And then from there, we're
gonna add a new action called
dependency review action.
I'm not gonna use this
one because I already have
another sample pipeline,
which technically does about
the same A few details here,
but I just use the defaults.
We run this pipeline out of an
automatic trigger, so whenever
there is a branch or the
main branch update, my pull
request is kicking in, and
that's triggering the pipeline
action The job we're running
is identical to the previous
example I showed you, use
the action dependency review.
So nothing too specific,
it's just an actions pipeline
What I did in preparation
for this demo is navigating
to my Ruby folder.
This is a Ruby example.
Gem is where you use package
management, and what we can do
here is updating the package
file, where I'm gonna add
example package, but it is
actually a known one called
nokogiri, and that's just
the name of the package.
And I think it's
respecting the syntax.
That's good.
And version one ten zero
is the one with known
vulnerabilities, and I'm
gonna add a little comment.
This is just for the demo
I'm saving the changes.
I'm gonna use the new branch
Or maybe keeping main because
my pull request is linked to
main I added the new package,
and then here you can see
that my dependency review task
obviously started running.
I speed up that part or
removed that part from
the demo recording.
But what it does here is
providing more insights.
So it detects a
vulnerable package.
By the way, it also identifies
that I didn't update my
open source license, but
then more below, it's
showing extensive details
about the vulnerabilities.
Now, up to this level, you
might go like, "Okay, what's
the difference now between
using the built-in Dependabot
and using an additional
dependency review pipeline?"
The big difference is
the review is literally
doing the review.
It's gonna detect
probably about the same.
I didn't check it for all
my repos, but I'm pretty
sure that anything that
the dependency review will
detect as a potential package
vulnerability will be detected
by Dependabot as well.
The big difference, however,
is that instead of just
running the review to identify
vulnerabilities, Dependabot is
adding not just the detection,
but also allowing you to
automatically fix and getting
that recommendation to fix it.
So it's a bit more automation.
It's a bit more, not just
detecting, but also providing
the mitigation steps.
Closing of this is why
not enabling both of them?
Again, there's a
bit of overlap.
Might be a bit specific
for your repos, your
company policies.
I heard from customers, some
of them are using dependency
review just to get a view
on the vulnerabilities
and then obviously
preferably also enabling
Dependabot on top of that.
I think that's pretty much
it on this part of the
demo, so let's go back to
the presentation to wrap
up the module and getting
ready for the next one
Moving on, we got E, where I
picked environment protection
rules, which is a GitHub
capability placing gates
like quality gates, security
gates if you want, around
sensitive deployments.
What that means is before
an actions GitHub pipeline
workflow is reaching
production, you can require
that approval restricting
which branches may deploy,
maybe never deploy, or
in between maybe giving
you a waiting state
where you as human beings
can do the validation.
And then we also have
enterprise security policies.
Those ones provide an
organization-wide guardrail
behind any of those decisions.
What they mainly do is helping
your teams, like your DevOps
teams, developer teams,
follow like a consistent
baseline for repositories,
actions, access, security
features, anything you pretty
much use as a company within
your GitHub environment
Next one is the letter
F, where I decided that F
to me stands for forking
and fork protection.
So for example, any
workflow that you trigger
from a fork should never,
and not automatically,
but never automatically
receive repository secrets.
Why?
Because the code came from
outside the trusted boundary.
GitHub therefore limits
secret access and also
requires, if you enable it,
deliberately approval in
certain sensitive cases.
Another option here that I
added is FedRAMP, which is
mainly compliance related,
not specifically security,
but in the end it's still
talking about protection.
What that means is if,
let's say, you're like a
US government compliance
framework for cloud systems.
For regulated work, the
platform configuration, your
operating processes like you
doing DevOps and all that
evidence needs to be supported
to have that required
FedRAMP control level.
It might be different in
Europe, might be different
in Asia, just one example
out of the US government
compliance framework.
Next we have the letter
G. Oh, one too far.
Letter G. G has a little
bit more options here.
So G to me covers
a lot of good old
DevSecOps foundations.
First of all, obviously GitHub
Advanced Security, already
talked about it, bringing
in code scanning, secret
scanning, dependency insights,
and any other related
security capabilities into
your developer environment.
Next we have GitHub actions,
running CI/CD pipelines,
automating builds, tests,
and integrating security,
and then obviously
deploying into staging
in ultimately production.
Another really cool one
is GPG commit signing.
What that one is doing,
helping you proving that a
commit came from a trusted
entity and it was never
really changed, modified,
getting compromised.
And then last, I hope it
makes sense to everyone,
the .gitignore file.
It keeps generated files,
local settings like the
.env environment file and
other unwanted content out
of your version control.
Now keep in mind, it's no…
it's not an excuse for having
like secrets in a file and
then moving it into gitignore.
So it's more like just
making sure that what
should not be moved into
source control should be
part of the gitignore.
But it's not 100%
security fix.
Also quite important
Let's continue.
I think we're about halfway
in, and we got the letter
H, a little bit short in
security capabilities, but I
came up with two scenarios.
Actually one, it's
overall hardening.
Hardening runners, the
virtual machines running the
pipelines, whether you use
the GitHub runners or if you
use the Azure DevOps agents,
which behind the scenes are
also GitHub runners now, or
you're overall running your
on-prem self-hosted, anything
here is valid for servers.
Hardening them, protecting
them, securing them
network-wise, but also patch
level, run them isolated,
do the monitoring, and
then also giving you that
least amount of privilege
access to do the job.
Self-hosted runners
need extra care.
Why?
Because you own
the life cycle.
It's more responsibility
for you as a DevOps team,
and then you also need to
take care of, for example,
network exposure, patching,
keeping them up to date.
That's what it means.
Hardening overall is that
broader discipline of overall
reducing attack surface.
Removing any software you
don't need anymore, keeping
your systems patched.
Again, tightening
permissions, protecting your
credentials, maybe adding
multi-factor authentication
out of like Entra ID if
that's your prime backend.
Integrating trusted
dependencies, making sure that
your config files are using
default settings instead of,
for example, adding secrets,
confidential information into
your environment variable file
Moving on, we have I
as in infrastructure
as code scanning using
code security checks and
also incident reporting.
I picked infrastructure
as code scanning because
everyone, I hope if you're
using cloud at least, is
using Azure, using Terraform,
Bicep, AWS, ARM templates,
Kubernetes YAML files, and so
many more code files overall,
meaning similar definitions
before you're gonna bring them
into your cloud environment.
Now, it can catch public
exposure, like if you move
it into a GitHub repo,
you're gonna clone it,
you're gonna copy it, you
find some examples online.
You never really know what
might be a potential security
risk for your environment.
Think about potential
weak identity settings or
missing encryption during
a review when fixes are,
like, easy to deal with as
long as you're still in the
development phase, right?
Incident response, on the
other side, begins when your
prevention is not enough,
confirming what happened,
but then also containing
the impact, mitigating the
problem, preserving evidence
obviously removing the root
cause of the problem, but
then also safely recovering
and then feeding it back
to your knowledge system,
which could be an AI
assistant or documenting
it in DevOps or GitHub.
Wikis could also help you
in overall incident response
The letter J I picked the
JSON web tokens, JWT tokens,
as we typically call them.
Now, if you're new to the
concept, a JWT token is
like a, a signed package, a
claim such as who's making
the request, but also who
issued the token, like
Entra ID or GitHub when
you're authenticating with
a GitHub account, and it
also identifies when that
token is getting expired.
Within GitHub actions, you can
create short-lived JWT tokens,
and they're really, I would
say, the central piece of
keyless cloud authentication.
What you can do is out of your
workflow, proving that the
identity is a cloud provider,
which then from there you're
gonna issue temporary access.
If you're familiar with
OIDC, which I'll talk about
a little bit later on, it's
one of those improvements,
you could say, into the
whole DevOps security from an
authentication perspective,
where you no longer need to
create static secrets and
keys inside GitHub secret
variables, but now you can
actually rely on OIDC to,
for example, reach out to
Azure, get a token to run
that one pipeline based
Bicep Terraform Azure CLI
deployment task Next we
have keyless authentication.
Again, it's OIDC, and as you
can see we also should talk a
little bit about key rotation.
So overall, it's about
authentication, preferably
not using hard-coded
passwords anymore.
If you use them, please
enable multi-factor
authentication, and again,
already mentioned right
before, for anything that's
pipeline related, try to move
into OIDC federated accounts
where, again, like Azure
and GitHub as an example,
deploying out of a GitHub
pipeline into Azure without
any hard-coded secrets, no
more service principles.
That's really what it means
Next is the letter L. Gonna
take a little brief here.
L, for me, combines
license compliancy,
repository license, but
also least privilege.
Nothing really new,
already talked about it.
Dependency review can flag
your packages, allowing
you to identify whose
open source licenses are
providing any conflicts
with maybe your legal or
distribution requirements.
So what you can do is adding
a license file as part of
the repo, and that makes
the rules for using your own
project clear to everyone.
So what that means is it's
not gonna modify any of your
licensing, but if you build
an open source project,
you would preferably add a
license file where you're
gonna explain hey, this is
what you as my contributor,
as my user of the repo and
the code within are allowed
to use or to do with it.
And then least privilege,
obviously, is the good
old foundational security
principle, connecting
users, applications,
tokens, workflows, you
think of it, you name it,
and should receive only the
access that is required.
A DevOps engineer doesn't
need full admin permissions in
Azure, doesn't need full admin
permissions in an Azure DevOps
environment, in a GitHub
environment, or anything
else that you're managing.
For like long living
permissions, I would say
try to step away from
those where the benefit
is smaller permissions,
meaning smaller blast
radius if something would
still potentially go wrong
Next M is protection
for the branches like
merge protection and
multi-factor authentication.
MFA or 2FA or fifteen FA, I
have no idea how many factor
authentications you wanna use,
but most important is don't
just rely on a password, but
add something else into it.
Windows Hello to log on to
your development workstation
using an authenticator app
that's gonna ask you for
biometric validation, whether
it's like smiling at a face
on your iPhone or like using
fingerprint on an Android,
something like that, right?
That's what we're
talking about here.
The reason why I hope I
don't have to explain why
MFA or 2FA is so important,
but in short, it just allows
you to make it harder to
steal your credentials.
I personally think that
any organization should
always enforce MFA, 2FA
at least for every account
with any important code
or settings access.
And maybe that's not even
valid anymore because I
guess nowadays, with all the
cyberattacks, I guess any
employee from any kind of
organization is becoming a
potential security threat.
So any user connecting
to corporate information
should always
authenticate passwordless.
That's the main message.
Second topic here
is merge protection.
Merge protection is a setting
inside your source control on
the GitHub site, Azure DevOps,
I'm pretty sure in other
source control and DevOps
tools, really safeguarding the
integration of unsecured code
into a branch, making sure
that you're not only blocking
yourself from overriding, but
defining specific rule sets.
A rule set can go
pretty granular, really
powerful capability.
For example the easiest one
is requiring reviews, asking
your peer developers to check
code before it can be merged.
You could also take it a
step further and defining
specific checks integrating
the signed commits that
I talked about before, or
integrating explicit approval
on top of a branch before a
change can actually be merged.
Nowadays with, for example,
GitHub Copilot code review
or the Dependabot integration
I talked about before, like
the autofix, you always
wanna keep that approval
before it's running the
code changes, raising a
PR, and then you're gonna
perform the branch merge.
Don't hand that over to
an AI engine to do that.
Make sure that you
as a DevOps engineer
know what's happening,
recognize the security
implications, and make sure
you keep control of that.
I think we're way more than
half in, so actually making
good progress here, I hope.
For N, I picked NIST.
NIST is one of those
security frameworks where the
security software development
framework is the full name,
and it gives organizations
and individual repos if you
want, a practical structure
for preparing, protecting,
producing, like the three
Ps in DevOps, and responding
around secure software.
I think it's really useful
as a common language, like
a common framework for
engineering governance
teams, developer teams.
On the project level
here, I'm integrating NPM
audit, like if you do node
packages out of node package
management, you can do NPM,
or if you do .NET Nuget,
you can run the auditing.
And what auditing is doing is
comparing dependency versions
with known vulnerability data.
Like a little bit what
Dependabot is doing, but
it's slightly different.
Overall, pretty powerful to
help you protecting your repos
O is for me in this alphabet
overview of security
capabilities, OpenID
Connect and organizational
security policies.
OpenID Connect is the
mechanism, authentication
mechanism already talked
about it multiple times.
That allows, for example,
GitHub actions to exchange
that short-living identity
token for temporary cloud
access to Azure, AWS, Google
Cloud, any other environment.
But then also more
important, avoiding needing
permanent credentials
that you're gonna store
inside repository secrets.
You don't have to
do that anymore.
That's the main thing.
Next to that, there's also
this trust relationship,
allowing you to really
restrict to the full
organization individual
repos all the way down to
a branch and environment,
or even inside a workflow.
Second piece is organizational
security policies.
Those ones allow you to just
integrate good practice,
best practices, repeatable on
top of the GitHub enterprise
organizational level.
Controlling the repos, who
can create them, who can
manage them, integrating
the runtime of actions,
like who can run actions.
Enabling security features
like, again, the three pillars
of GitHub advanced security
and then again making sure
that it's not just for one
repo, but pretty much any
repo that you get created
within your organization
Moving on, I got a longer
list here with the letter P.
Must be because it's Peter.
Push protection, policy as
code, pull requests, and
private versus public repos
Again, quite a lot here.
I'll start with
push protection.
Push protection detects likely
secrets, like what I talked
about secret protection,
but now you enable that
extra little settings.
I'm pretty sure I can show
you that in a demo in a
second, where it's actually
not just detecting the secrets
that you expose, which again
should never happen, but we
know that always happens.
Where now if you have a secret
from any of those detectable
partners, then before you
would still be able to commit.
Once it arrives in the
GitHub repo, it would get
detected, where now with push
protection, it's actually
running locally and the Git
commit is no longer working.
Pull request re… Oh, sorry,
policy as code is just a set
of rule, rules allowing you
to just define rule bases.
Nothing too hard,
easy to understand.
Pull request reviews, again,
make sure that humans are
still in the loop nowadays
with AI becoming more and more
visible and more important.
But overall, pull request
reviews is gonna add the
context and shared ownership
before making changes.
And then the choice between
private public repos, I
guess it all makes sense.
Private repos are the ones
you should use for any
internal company, corporate
information, sample code,
production ready code.
Where public repos by default
means the whole internet,
everyone can use them.
And it's not exactly the
same thing as open source,
but that's where I talked
about licensing before.
If you have any public repos
in GitHub, know that a lot of
the baseline GitHub advanced
security capabilities are
already coming for free.
Like the secret scanning is
part of it, Dependabot can
be used for free, and CodeQL
can be used as well up to a
certain extent for free as
well I guess we're almost
there, but we're not done yet.
So moving on, the letter
Q for me is quality gates
and then also branch rule
sets, which are partly
covering the same thing.
So what in short
are quality gates?
A quality gate is the
mechanism in GitHub also
exists in Azure DevOps
for years already, turning
just an important flag a,
a check if you want, into
an actual security barrier.
Like you cannot merge
because you're not
following the guidelines.
Or another example that
I always use in like
an Azure context is
run an Azure command to
check Azure policies.
Why would you deploy a
virtual machine if then the
policy is gonna block you?
That's like in the end
a failing pipeline.
So that's in short the
mechanism allowing you to
bring in security, overall
quality validations before
performing a merge, and
then maybe even before
running a deployment
from one stage to another
The R is, again, a
little bit longer.
Three topics I
picked out here.
Role-based access, repo
rulesets, and risk scoring.
Role-based access is back
to the good old least
privilege, least permissions.
You don't need to be
a full admin to do
your day-to-day job.
That's what it means.
Repository rulesets,
already talked about, so
again, applying consistent
branch protections, tag
protections in GitHub across
one or more repositories.
Risk scoring is a little
bit less known, I think, but
what it helps you doing is
prioritizing the results by
combining overall technology
factors, I call them, like
severity, exploitability,
exposure, business impact,
business risk, and then
giving you some sort of
a dashboard overview.
The main goal of risk
scoring is not to simplify
but generate more findings.
It's really about creating a
limited or… Let me rewrite.
The goal is not simply to
generate more findings.
It is to direct limited
attention to the actual
issue, maybe bringing in
some AI integration as well.
As is the longest, I guess
this is the longest list
of security features,
but already talked about
quite a lot of them.
Secret scanning is really
about finding those
exposed credentials.
Static application security
testing is analyzing
source code before your
workload is running.
So using examination, you
can bring in third-party
components, you can bring
in the GitHub advanced
security components.
That would be the baseline.
But let's say you go like I
already have a third-party
scanning tool," I don't
know, SonarCloud, SonarQube
Snyk, Mint WhiteSource
Bolt from the past.
There's so many different
SAST security tools.
A lot of them are
actually supported within
GitHub, so you don't
have to migrate away.
I could only recommend you
maybe look into capabilities,
what's the cost, how is
the cost getting budgeted,
and then maybe gradually
shifting away from any
third-party scanning tool
into GitHub Advanced Security.
Why would you pay more,
why would you bring in
more complexity if the
baseline platform can
already provide it?
Next is software
bill of material.
It's giving you this list
like a record, right?
Identifying what software
components are included in
your repo, in your workload
that you're gonna deploy.
Shifting left is really
the mindset, DevSecOps,
integrate security in
everything you do in DevOps.
Moving from it's live in
production, we're gonna rely
on the network security,
authentication security and
whatnot, but now bringing
it all the way to the left,
meaning that it's not only
faster to detect, but it's
also saving you headaches,
probably cheaper to fix
the problem, and maybe not
even exposing any issues
into real world production
public environment where you
don't wanna be like coming
up on, I don't know, the
late night news being part
of a ransomware attack,
cybersecurity attack,
because it might not only
cost you a lot of money,
it might actually harm your
company overall as well.
The closer shifting left for
detecting security problems,
the better protection you
could say that you have.
And then one other option here
is the security markdown file,
and that's again a pretty easy
option inside each and every
repo you have to inform anyone
using the repo how to actually
report vulnerabilities.
So it's not a security
protection as such, but it's
really telling your users,
the contributors of the repo,
what they should do if they
detect any security issues
within the repo that you're
managing So let me show you
what secret scanning in GitHub
Advanced Security looks like,
where this demo will be a
little bit shorter because
it's only one little task, but
I would say super powerful and
actually extremely relevant
and important to enable it.
Now, just to make sure
you get a good idea, I'm
using a private repo.
Now, why do I use a
private repo in this case?
Because in my demo
environment, if I would create
a public repo as I talked
about in the presentation,
public GitHub repos have
secret scanning enabled.
So I needed to go through
a little bit of a side
path, you could say,
to simulate my demo.
Now, what is the
starting point?
Imagine I have my code
on my local machine.
I'm synchronizing with my
GitHub repos and inside my
application settings JSON,
my developer, in this case
myself, stored a GitHub token.
I'm not exposing
any secrets per se.
Technically I am, but this is
a demo personal access token.
So that's where I just
wanna make sure that I'm not
overexposing information.
But we made a mistake as a
developer, you could say,
where now we have this token
from GitHub or any other
vendor that I talked about
listed in our code base.
Now, to enable, I would
need to go into settings.
And again, if you do have
the GitHub Advanced Security
licensing, you would navigate
to Advanced Security,
where down here you're
gonna find Secret Scanning.
In my case, because again,
I don't have enterprise or
any organizations behind
it, and I didn't wanna focus
too specific on enterprise
capabilities only because
I guess quite some of
you viewing these videos
are not just enterprise
customers, I need to
switch to a public repo.
So I'm gonna move to the
General section and then
changing my visibility
from private to public.
I guess I need to
provide some admin
Credentials, they were
cached apparently,
so that's positive.
Now it's gonna allow me
to actually open up my
security settings again.
And now you can see
down here that we do
have secret protection.
Now, if you create a public
repo from scratch, it's
automatically enabled.
Since now I switched from
private to public, it's
not automatically enabled.
So I'm gonna enable this Yes,
I wanna use secret protection.
And on top of that,
as explained in the
presentation, I can also
enable push protection.
So I got my two options
enabled, and from here,
I navigate to Security,
Secret scanning, and you
can see that there is an
immediate alert getting
created, like forty-seven
seconds ago, basically
once I enabled my secret
scanning, and it's detecting
the personal access token.
It's in historical
synchronized repos,
you could say.
So the big benefit is that
once you enable secret
scanning from a private
repo or, and switch from
private to public, and you
enable it, it's gonna look
into your code base and
immediately detecting it.
Now, another thing that I
wanna show you here is that
push protection, right?
So for example, I go into
my code base and gonna
update any of my files,
not too important And I'm
gonna add yet another secret
Using my demo key.
When I now commit my changes
It's telling me here Peter,
you cannot do that." Why not?
Because secret scanning
is detecting that secret.
I can flag here it's being
used for testing, it's a
false positive, or it's
okay, I know, I'll fix it
later, which I think is not
really according secret or
security best practices.
So what it means is that
out of that push protection,
it's now also blocking
me from synchronizing.
I showed you from it in
the GitHub portal, but in
the end, if I would go back
to my local development
workstation, you inject the
code or the key over there.
Trying to commit, that will
work local, but then when
I try to sync back to the
repo, it will tell me in the
Git log errors that I cannot
synchronize because of the
secret scanning protection.
So end-to-end, hundred
percent secured, if
obviously you enable not
only secret scanning, but
also the push protection.
So with that, I'm gonna wrap
it up here and switching back
to the last couple of things
in our secret scanning module.
Feels like we're getting
closer to the end of
the alphabet, so give me
another couple of minutes
to walk you through.
In the T overview, I
got controlling access
before trouble starts.
What this means
is token scoping.
Token scoping by default
GitHub token as one of
the known environment
variables provide you
only the permissions that
each job actually needs.
It's like that least
amount of privilege.
Threat modeling is the
scenario, the concept if
you want, but there's also
Microsoft Threat Modeling
tool, a free tool that allows
you to validate questions,
checking potential known
vulnerabilities already, but
not from a coding perspective.
What is getting built, what
could go wrong, what controls
should be designed before
your code can be released.
Two-factor authentication,
multi-factor authentication,
already talked about in a
previous slide, so not gonna
repeat all of that The U to me
is everything around updates.
Update automation and then
updates from an upstream
dependency security.
So what that means automated
version updates for example,
bringing in Dependabot
together with Autofix,
together with now the GitHub
Copilot capability allows
you to perform like routine
package checks as I would
call it, like moving out
that maintenance that nobody
really wants to do, like
the dull tasks or the toil
but having it gradually
integrating instead of doing
this big, bulky, large, risky
as well backlog to build up.
If you have like a pull
request, so let's say you're
getting code in a repo, you
got vulnerability scanning,
and then you do update
automation using Dependabot,
it's gonna create a pull
request, but the pull request
still needs testing, it needs
review, it needs validation.
But at least the discovery
and the proposal like how
to fix and mitigate the
vulnerability, that's all
part of this scenario.
So the more you can automate
this task, the more time
you have available for
other equal or maybe
even more important work.
And then upstream dependency
security, that's the
piece that's gonna ask
you to look beyond a
specific version number.
Is the project maintained?
What are the releases?
Are they signed, yes or no?
How quickly are
vulnerabilities
getting addressed,
detected and addressed?
And then what happens
if that dependency or
the build pipeline is
getting compromised?
Like just helping you, again,
maximizing the security of
your dependency packages.
We're getting close where
for V I talked about
vulnerability management,
and you can see here once
more we're going back to
Dependabots and primarily
the alerts out of it.
Finding a vulnerability
is, to me, just the
beginning of the problem.
We need to validate,
understand where the affected
component is used, assessing
severity and exposure.
Also assigning ownership
and tracking remediation.
Dismissal should mean we,
like you as the DevOps
engineer, made a documented
risk decision, not that we
wanted a clear dashboard.
In the end, dashboards
are just there to help you
getting a clearer view.
It's not the security
mitigation on its own
Specific findings may
need to be reopened.
You might have an issue
a couple of weeks, you
fixed it, closed it,
mitigated, and maybe couple
of days, weeks later you
might need to reopen it.
So all that context, all that
triaging, dismissing, and
so on is all part of this.
We're almost there.
W, workflows and webhooks.
GitHub actions, workflows,
there's no way around it.
It's not a security
mechanism as such, but all
the security capabilities
that I talked about most of
them are actually part…
potential part of GitHub
actions, workflows.
Easy as that.
Webhooks is the event
handler allowing you to send
notifications, for example,
to typically external systems,
integrating with Teams,
integrating with Slack,
integrating with ServiceNow,
and so many other examples.
Just allowing you to
optimize how you deal
with monitoring, how you
deal with observability,
and then overall
integrating automation.
Because you could send an API
call, you could send an email
to another third-party system
where then at that moment
in time, when it arrives at
the endpoint, it's actually
triggering another task
inside that other platform
X is representing cross-site
scripting and injection.
So same thing what I
talked about with CodeQL.
So what is cross-site
scripting injection?
So these security tracks
security traps, sorry, happen
when you have untrusted
input getting treated as
an executable content,
like someone trying to run
something on a web app, maybe
connecting to a database where
it really honestly depends on
the context, like encoding,
I don't know, output in a
browser using parameterized
queries, like searching like
a SQL database backend in
like a retail website or any
other, and then attacker,
a hacker is trying to steal
credit card information,
something like that.
Or integrating, building shell
commands as part of a string,
validating inputs integrating
APIs, whatever you think
of, it could all be part of
this cross-site scripting.
Code scanning is here as well.
So why do I refer
to code scanning?
Because code scanning can now,
using CodeQL in GitHub and
in Azure DevOps, can identify
a lot of these risky data
flaws OWASP that I mentioned,
where now I actually think I
should update my slide and add
OWASP in the O slide as well.
But it allows you to
integrate, again, securing
design, carefully reviewing
everything that's already
part of your code.
Two more to go.
Why?
I have no idea.
I came up with YAML.
YAML on its own is not
a security feature, but
YAML is the code base
for GitHub actions.
What you can do inside
GitHub actions is using the
permissions key, and that's
defining that GitHub token
that I talked about before
has certain permissions
to perform certain tasks.
So again, once more, rather
than accepting this broad
default "Hey, GitHub token,
I trust you. You can do
pretty much whatever you want
using the user permissions."
You're gonna declare explicit
permissions and maybe starting
with read-only access.
You only need to elevate
if the job requires you
to actually write code to
update, publish a package, to
create an identity token, or
maybe updating a deployment.
Everything else should always
have read permissions only.
Looks like we did it with the
full alphabet, so I'm gonna
nicely close and wrap it up.
The Z here stands
for Zero Trust.
It's one of those things
that within Microsoft, within
GitHub, we think is the
baseline for good security.
Zero Trust means never trust
automatically, but then always
explicitly verify, and at
the same time assume breach.
What that means in practice is
every identity, every request
must prove that it's allowed
to perform the task, to do
what it's asking to do, and
then even when it's coming
from a trusted workstation
from within the network.
Don't trust anything,
don't trust anyone.
Access should always be
scoped, narrowly scoped, least
amount of privilege, least
amount of permissions, private
endpoints in Azure, allowing
that a web app connecting to
a database for like a retail
workload, the web app can
only connect to the database.
The database only
accepts connectivity
from the app layer.
Nothing else, nothing more.
That's the whole idea.
I added a link here,
github.com/microsoftzerotrust,
or if you go to
Microsoft directly, like
learn.microsoft.com and
you look for Zero Trust,
it's gonna give you
all those explanations.
So with that, we're close to
the end of this session here,
but I'm not done yet because
I got even more to share.
What am I sharing?
First of all, I did a similar
but less prepared because
it was really the first
time on the spot almost.
Did this presentation at
the DevOps and PowerShell
Summit here in Bellevue
a couple of months ago.
Updated the deck obviously,
because security is literally
changing almost every week.
Now, what I have is
a full demo repo.
A lot of the demos that
I integrated here that I
mentioned, but not always
had a lot of time, you can go
through that repo and you got
all those demos available.
Next to that, in my previous
role at Microsoft, where
I was a technical trainer
for Azure architecting and
DevOps primarily, I recorded
like readiness videos.
They're published on
YouTube, ak.ms/gh-500.
It's a couple of hours
content helping you getting
ready for the GitHub Advanced
Security Exam credential.
So feel free to use them.
They're open source.
You can watch the videos.
You can sorry, go
through all the demos.
That's really the
message, and that's all
I wanted to talk about.
So with that, I'm
gonna close out.
I spent about forty-five
minutes, so I hope
you were here with me.
If not, scroll back, go fast
forward, go back, rewind,
and zoom in on the specifics
that might be valid for
your specific scenarios.
Thank you so much for joining.
Thanks for participating,
and enjoy the rest
of the conference.